Changes in your diet not
only affect you physically,
physiologically inside,
but also mentally,
how well you think,
psychologically,
how well you feel.
But you’ll never know just
how good you can feel
until you put it to the test
and try eating healthy.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the surprising
versatility of fecal transplants.
Did you know they can be used
to treat clinical conditions
like ulcerative colitis,
depression,
bipolar disorder,
and alcoholism?
Here’s the story.
Plant-based foods and the microbiome
in the preservation of health
and prevention of disease.
We have evidence that high-fiber,
plant-based diets can prevent
many different common diseases,
maybe through the effect
that these diets have on the
composition and metabolic activity
of our microbiome,
the bacteria in our gut.
Good gut bugs in our colon
eat the plant residues and
spit out health-promoting and
cancer-suppressing metabolites.
Like fiber is metabolized
to short-chain fatty acids,
which have profound
anti-inflammatory,
anti-cancer properties.
And we have special fiber-feeding
microbes that chew through
the plant cell walls and release
all the anti-inflammatory,
antioxidant, and
anticancer goodies inside.
So, how many whole plant foods
do we have to eat?
All the evidence points to
a physiological need
for about 50 grams
of fiber a day,
which is what is contained
in the traditional African diet
and is associated with the prevention
of common Western chronic diseases.
This is up to twice
the recommended minimum
and three times the current
intake in the United States.
How can you prove the microbiome
is involved though?
Fecal transplantation --
stool transplants.
One man's trash,
another man's treasure.
Currently, donor fecal microbiota
transplantation is the optimum
therapeutic approach for recurrent
Clostridium difficile infection.
C. diff is today considered the most
common hospital-acquired cause
of diarrhea. It's a life-threatening
infection that can rear its ugly head
when your good gut bugs have been
wiped out by antibiotics.
So to get rid of it, all we need
are more good gut bugs,
which can be provided
by a healthy donor
through the infusion of a liquid
suspension of the donor's stool.
We are winning with poo.
Fecal transplants have proven
their worth in the management
of recurrent C. diff diarrhea,
with cure rates up to 90%.
Because of this success, fecal
transplants have been suggested
as a potential treatment in other
gastrointestinal diseases.
For example, the inflammatory bowel
disease known as ulcerative colitis.
There have been four
randomized controlled trials,
and fecal transplants appear to nearly
double clinical remission rates.
But what about
non-gastrointestinal disorders?
Here's a case study
of a series of fecal transplants
for multiple sclerosis (MS).
The patient experienced improvements
in their microbiome,
more of those fiber-feeding
anti-inflammatory bacteria.
And there was a significant increase
in the levels of brain derived
neurotrophic factor,
which is suggested to play
a neuroprotective role in MS,
as well as
both subjective and objective
evidence of improved walking,
which was the patient's
primary MS symptom.
Now, to give the new fiber feeders
something to chew on,
the patient was put on
a high fiber diet, which is great.
But just putting people on
a plant-based diet alone may help,
stool transplants or not,
since standard Western diets
promote dysbiosis,
a bad bug gut imbalance, and
neuroinflammation in MS,
while plant-based high-fiber
diets decrease MS risks.
Randomized, placebo-controlled trials
will be needed to tease that out,
but in the meanwhile we can
certainly build up good gut bugs
the old-fashioned way by eating
fiber-rich whole plant foods.
What about fecal transplants
for depression?
Interest in the gut microbiome
and its role in health has exploded
just in the last few years. Does any
of this have relevance in psychiatry?
Maybe so. Several studies
demonstrate microbiome differences
between depressed persons
and non-depressed persons.
And after all, an imbalance in
neurotransmitters is implicated
in the cause of depression,
and the gut microbiome is known
to synthesize large quantities
of these same neuroactive substances,
like serotonin and dopamine.
And there's a major information
highway from the gut to the brain
called the vagus nerve that could
potentially alter mood states.
Early fecal transplants were
delivered from the bottom up,
through colonoscopy,
but now
we have crapsules -- encapsulated
feces to make it easier to swap stool.
Here's a case report of a 79-year-old
woman who suffered a tragedy
and subsequently lost her appetite,
became introverted, drowsy,
and stayed in bed all day,
wasting away 55 pounds
over the next six months.
She was hospitalized for
depression and prescribed
multiple anti-depressant drugs,
but to no avail.
So, what the heck, they stopped
the drugs and tried a fecal transplant.
The stool donor was her own
6-year-old great-grandson,
who had a good appetite,
an outgoing personality,
and a disciplinary stool --
I don't even know what that means.
Four days after the fecal transplant,
she started feeling better,
and by two weeks
she was frankly euphoric.
She was able to go back home,
and within six weeks
all was back to normal.
What about a fecal transplant
for bipolar disorder?
The poor woman was in and out of
psych hospitals with manic depression
until she got a fecal transplant
with stool from her husband --
that 's romantic --
and within six months
she was symptom free.
This case report was published
in 2020, so symptom free for years,
no longer on medication, and has
lost more than 70 pounds to boot,
either because she got slim hubby stool
or just being off her psych meds.
She went from being
functionally disabled
to running a small business
and has published two books.
What about alcohol dependence?
Alcoholism has traditionally
been considered exclusively
a brain disorder, but, hey,
all these other psychiatric syndromes
seem to have links to the gut.
So they compared the guts
of alcoholics to nonalcoholics,
and they found that some
alcohol-dependent subjects
developed gut leakiness,
which was associated
with higher alcohol craving.
Okay, but maybe instead
of the gut issues somehow
leading to alcohol cravings,
the alcohol led to the gut issues.
Alcohol may have a toxic effect
on the gut wall, but both groups
were consuming the same
amount of alcohol at the time,
so maybe there is some kind
of gut connection after all.
This was the study that
blew people's minds.
The transplant of feces
from alcoholics
into mice induced
an alcohol preference.
These were mice without any
previous contact with alcohol,
all of a sudden spontaneously
preferring alcohol.
Normally mice don't
really like alcohol,
but feed them some feces
from an alcoholic human,
and they do
a 180-degree switch.
So wait. Are you saying that gut bugs
can determine alcohol craving?
There's only one way to find out,
and that's put it to the test.
A randomized, double-blind, clinical
trial of fecal microbiota transplant
for alcohol use disorder,
which is the current clinical
term for alcoholism.
They took alcoholics
with liver cirrhosis
and active problem drinking
and randomized them
to get either a placebo enema
or a fecal transplant enema.
And within two weeks, alcohol
cravings reduced significantly
in 90% of the fecal transplant cases
versus just 30%
in placebo cases.
And this was validated by pee tests
showing that they were drinking
significantly less too,
with improved cognition and
psychosocial quality of life.
Now this is all still
just experimental,
and not without
potential downsides.
Yes, they're working on ways to make
stool transplants more palatable.
On balance, they've largely
been found to be safe,
though there have been cases
of bad bugs being transferred
from donors, even a fatal case.
And there's even a theoretical risk
you could be transplanted
with cancer cells, making it
the gift that keeps on giving,
but in a bad way.
In our next story,
we look at what’s more important:
probiotics or prebiotics?
And where can
we best get them?
Virtually every day,
we are all confronted
with the activity
of our intestine,
and it is no surprise that
at least some of us
have developed a fascination
with our intestinal condition
and its relation to
health and disease.
Over the last years, the
intestinal microbiota,
our gut flora, has
been identified as like
a fascinating ‘new organ,’
with all sorts of functions.
Well, if the bacteria in our gut
make up a whole separate
organ inside our body,
what about doing
an organ transplant?
What would happen if you
transferred intestinal bacteria
from lean people
into obese people?
Researchers figured that rebalancing
the obesity-causing bacteria
with an infusion
of gut bacteria
from a lean person
might help.
Now, they wanted this to
be a placebo-controlled study,
which for drugs is easy:
give a sugar pill.
But, when you’re sticking
a tube down people’s throats
and transplanting feces,
I’m thinkin’ what do you
use as a poop placebo?
A poop-cebo, if you will!
Both the donors and the subjects
brought in fresh stools,
and the subjects
were randomized
to either get
the donor’s stool
or get transplanted with
their own collected feces—
that was the placebo, you
just get your own back.
Okay, so what happened?
The insulin sensitivity
of the skinny donors
was up around 50;
that’s a good thing.
High insulin sensitivity means
low insulin resistance,
the cause of both type 2
diabetes and prediabetes.
The obese subjects
started out around 20,
and after an infusion
of their own feces,
they stayed
around 20.
But, the group of obese
donors getting the skinny
similarly started
low but shot up
near to where the
slim folks were.
It’s interesting: not all
lean donor stools
conveyed the same effect
on insulin sensitivity,
as some donors had
very significant effects,
the so-called
super-fecal donor,
whereas others had
little or no effect.
Turns out this super-donor effect
is most probably conveyed
by the amounts of short-chain
fatty acid-producing
intestinal bacteria
in their feces,
the food bacteria that thrive
off of the fiber we eat.
The short chain
fatty acids produced
by fiber-eating bacteria may
contribute to the release
of gut hormones that
may be the cause
of this beneficial improved
insulin sensitivity.
The successful use of
fecal transplantation
has recently attracted
considerable attention,
not only because
of its success,
but its capacity to prove
the cause and effect relationship
that the bacteria
we have in our gut
can affect
our metabolism.
But, within a few months,
the bacterial composition
returned back to baseline;
so, the effects on the obese
subjects were temporary.
We can get similar benefits
though, by just feeding
what few good gut bacteria
we may already have.
Say you have a shed
full of bunny rabbits.
Feed them pork rinds,
and they all die.
Yes, you can repopulate your shed
by infusing new bunnies,
but if you keep feeding
them pork rinds,
they’ll eventually
die off as well.
Whereas, even if you start off
with just a few bunnies,
if you feed them what
they’re meant to eat,
they’ll grow and
multiply and soon
you’ll be full of
fiber-eating bunnies.
Fecal transplants and probiotics
are only temporary fixes,
if we keep putting the
wrong fuel into our gut.
But, by eating prebiotics,
such as fiber, which means
increasing whole
plant food consumption,
we may select for and
foster the growth
of our own good bacteria.
However, such effects may abate
once the high-fiber
intake ceases.
Therefore, our dietary habits,
should include
a continuous consumption
of large quantities
of high-fiber foods
to improve our health.
And, if we don’t, we may be
starving our microbial self.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.